＜柱間：夢のようだった。
It was like a dream...
うちはと千手が手を組んだのだ。
The Uchiha and the Senju
formed an alliance.
もう多くの犠牲が出ることもない。
There would no longer
be any casualties,
多くの子供たちの死も
必要なくなる＞
nor would any more children
have to die.
＜　そして　俺たちは→
And so, we began
building our village.
一から里づくりを始めた＞
＜　その後　火の国と手を組み→
Later, we would ally
with the Land of Fire,
国と里が同等の立場で組織する→
and the creation of
a peaceful state
where nation and village stood
on equal footing also commenced.
平安の国づくりも始まった＞
＜　とにかく夢のようだった＞
In any case, it was like a dream.
My True Dream
SHINOBI ACADEMY
Do you remember how we used
to talk here when we were kids?
((柱間：覚えてるか？
ガキの頃に　ここで話したこと。
（マダラ）ああ。
Yeah...
（柱間）ここに
俺たちの集落をつくろう。
Let's build our settlement here!
（マダラ）えっ？
（柱間）その集落は→
Huh?
And make it so kids won't have
to kill each other!
子供が殺し合わなくて
いいようにする。
子供がちゃんと
強く大きくなるための→
We'll create a school where
kids can train and grow up stronger!
訓練する学校をつくる。
個人の能力や力に合わせて
任務を選べる。
Assign missions that fit
an individual's abilities and strengths!
んでもって　依頼レベルを→
Have superiors who can properly
assign ranks to commissions!
ちゃんと振り分けられる
上役を作る。
子供を激しい戦地へ送ったり
しなくていい集落だ。
It will be a place
where kids don't have to be sent
into harsh battlefronts.
（マダラ）フッ　そんなバカなこと
言ってんの　お前くらいだぞ。
You're pretty much the only one
spouting such nonsense.
お前は　どうなんだよ？
Well then, what about you?
悪くはねえな。
It doesn't sound bad at all.
Then it's decided!
だったら決まりぞ。
ああ。
Yeah... If that settlement
gets built here,
その集落つくったら
今度こそ　弟を→
then I could watch over
my little brother,
一望できる　ここから
しっかり守ってやる。
and protect him in this place
where you can see to no end!
フフッ。
ヘヘヘッ。
あれは　ただの夢の話だと
思ってた。
I thought we were just talking
about our dream.
つかもうとすれば→
They say where there's a will,
there's a way...
できないことは
なかったってのに　俺は…。
And yet, I...
これから夢が現実になる。
That dream is now becoming reality.
火の国を守る　影の忍の長→
The leader of shinobi who protects
the Land of Fire from the shadows.
名を火影　どうだ？
The Fire Shadow, or Hokage. Well?
何だ　それ。
What's that supposed to be?
The Land of Fire requests that
we select someone
火の国から里の代表を決めるよう
要請があったんだ。
who will represent the Village.
（柱間）お前に
長をやってほしいと思っている。
I'm considering naming you
to be our leader... the Hokage.
火影を。
もう　お前に兄弟はいないが→
You no longer have any siblings left...
この里の忍たちは→
But I'd like you to think of
all of the village shinobi as your siblings.
皆　お前の兄弟だと思ってほしい。
しっかりと
皆を見守ってほしいんだ。
I want you to protect them
with all your might.
（マダラ）うちはの兄弟すら
守れなかった　この俺に。
Even though I couldn't protect
my own Uchiha brethren?
瓦間。
（板間）ううっ　うっ…。
Kawarama...
（柱間）板間！　板間！
Itama!
（柱間）ああ～　うわぁ～！
くっ　うぅ…。
W-What happened?
ど　どうしたんだよ。
弟が　死んだ。
My little brother...died.
ここへ来るのは　川を見てると→
I come to the river
because I feel like
心の中のモヤモヤが
流されてく気がするからだ。
all the haziness in my heart gets
washed away as I stare at the water.
そうだったのか。
So that's what happened...
（柱間）マダラ　だっけか？
Your name's Madara, right?
お前も　そうだったりしてな。
I wonder if you're like me...
（柱間）お前　兄弟とかいるか？
Do you have siblings?
（マダラ）俺は　５人兄弟→
I'm one of five.
だった。
Well, there used to be five of us.
（柱間）
なぁ　もう　兄弟はいねえのか？
So...you don't have
any more siblings?
いや　１人だけ　弟が残ってる。
No... I have one younger brother left.
その弟だけは
何があろうと　俺が守る。
And I'll protect him,
no matter what!
お前の兄弟は？
What about you?
俺も１人残ってる
俺も　絶対に　弟は　守るつもりぞ。
I have one brother left too.
And I intend to protect him too,
no matter what.
（扉間）飛雷神斬り！
Flying Raijin Slice!
Izuna!
イズナ！
ハァ　ハァ。
弱気になってる暇なんて　ないぞ。
There's no time to
get weak right now!
うちはに　千手は
もちろんとして→
In addition to the Uchiha and Senju,
猿飛一族に　志村一族も
仲間に入りたいそうだからな。
it seems the Sarutobi and
the Shimura Clans also want to join.
ウソだろ。　ほんとかよ　それ。
Are you kidding? Are you serious?!
その他にも　まだまだ
この里は　どんどん大きくなるぞ。
And there are many others!
This village is going to
keep on expanding!
そろそろ
里の名前も決めないとな。
We're going to need to come up
with a name for the village too...
何か　案あるか？
Any thoughts?
（マダラ）木ノ葉隠れの里ってのは
どうだ？
How about...
The Village...Hidden in the Leaves?
（柱間）単純ぞ。　ひねりもないぞ。
見たままぞ。
It's too simple...
It's not imaginative.
You called it exactly as you saw it.
火影と　どう違うんだ　コラッ！
How's it different from "Hokage"?!
(てか　まだ直ってねえのか
その落ち込み癖))
And you still have that habit
of getting depressed easily!
＜長い時間かかったが→
It took a long time, but it felt like
俺たちは　昔の仲に
戻れた気がした＞
we were back to being
the friends we once were.
((それで　その火影ってのは
里にずっといて→
So you're saying
the role of the Hokage
is to stay in the village
and protect everyone?
みんなを見守る役目ってことだろ。
それもあるが
そういう意味だけじゃない。
There's that...
But he'll be even more significant.
これから　里づくりが
本格化するにあたって→
As village-building picks up speed,
the Hokage will get busier too.
火影も忙しくなる。
だから　お前のでかい顔岩を
この足もとの岩に彫る。
That's why I want to
have your likeness
carved into this cliff at our feet.
この里を守る　象徴だぞ。
As a symbol of
our village's protector!
冗談だろ。
You've got to be kidding!
顔が　イカツすぎるから　ほんの少し
手を加えるけどな。
Although...your face is a bit too stern...
so it will have to be softened
here and there.
てめえの情けねえ落ち込み顔より
ずっとマシだろ。
Well, it beats that sad mug of yours!
そんなに情けないぞ？
Is it that sad?
フフフ　ああ　十分すぎるほど
情けねえ。
Yeah... It's beyond sad.
（柱間）そうか。
（マダラ）フフフ。
Is that so?
（扉間）ここにいたのか。
こんなところで　なに油売ってる！
There you are!
What are you dawdling here for?
（扉間）火の国の大名たちが
会談に来る頃だぞ！
The Feudal Lords from the Land of Fire
will be here soon for the conference!
扉間か…。
It's Tobirama...
（扉間）火影だと？
何を勝手なことを。
For Hokage?!
That's not your choice!
マダラを長の候補として
推薦するまではいい。
To propose Madara as
a candidate for leader is fine...
だが　決定は
火の国と里の民意を聞きつつ→
But the final decision will be made
with the top officials,
after consulting with the Land of Fire
and the people of the village!
上役と相談して決める。
もう父上のときとは違う。
Things are different from Father's era!
しかし…。
そして　うちはマダラが→
But...
Besides, Madara Uchiha being chosen
as the leader won't happen.
長に選ばれることは　まずない。
皆わかってる。
Everyone knows...
里をつくった立役者は
兄者のほうだと。
You are the one who founded
this settlement, Big Brother.
それは　うちはの者たちまで
言ってることだ。
Even those from
the Uchiha say as much.
それに　兄者は
うちはの噂を知らないのか？
Furthermore, haven't you heard
the rumors about them?
やつらの瞳力は　憎しみの
強い者ほど強くあらわれる。
The stronger their hate,
the stronger their Visual Prowess
manifests itself.
写輪眼がそうだ。
The Sharingan is such a power.
何をしでかすかわからぬ連中だ。
これからの里にとって…。
They're unpredictable.
For the future of the village...
そういう言い方はよせ　扉間。
Stop talking like that, Tobirama!
ん？
ここに誰かいたような気がしたぞ。
I just felt someone's presence.
扉間　お前ならわかるだろ？
Tobirama, you would know.
いや　今はチャクラを練ってない。
話をそらすな　兄者。
No... I'm not infusing chakra right now.
Don't change the subject, Big Brother!
これからは
民主的な運営をやっていく。
From now on,
things will be run democratically.
異議はあるか？
Any objections?
(（柱間）いや　それでいい))
No... That's fine.
＜　そして俺は
初代火影となった＞
And so...
I became the First Hokage.
俺は　初代火影となった。
I became the First Hokage...
From the Era of Warring States...
（柱間）戦乱の世　忍と忍が→
where shinobi clans fought
and killed each other...
命を取り合う
一族同士の対立から→
the Uchiha and Senju joined together
to create the ideal shinobi village...
うちはと千手が手を取り合って
できた　忍の理想郷。
A shinobi village born
from the hope for peace...
平和を求め　生まれた忍里
それが　木ノ葉隠れの里だ。
That is the Village Hidden in the Leaves.
その　初代火影に　俺はなった。
And I became its First Hokage.
This is the stone tablet that has been
passed down the Uchiha for generations.
((マダラ：これは　うちはに
代々　伝わる石碑。
It's never been shown
to an outsider before.
他族に見せたことは一度もない。
The special text requires
Visual Prowess to decipher.
解読するには　瞳力が必要な
特別な読み物だ。
今の俺が　解読できるところまでに
こう書いてある。
This is what I'm able
to decipher so far...
"One god seeking stability
split into light and shadow.
「１つの神が安定を求め→
陰と陽に分極した
相反する２つは作用し合い→
"And it is these opposites together
that give rise
"to all things in this universe."
森羅万象を得る」。
これは
すべてに当てはまる道理だ。
This is a universal truth.
つまり　相反する２つの力が
協力することで→
In short, it states that
true happiness can be found
when two contrary powers
cooperate together.
本当の幸せがあるとうたっている。
However, it could be
interpreted differently.
だが　別のとらえ方もできる。
Hashirama...
柱間　俺が何も知らないと思うか？
Do you think I don't know
what's going on?
扉間のことは俺に任せてくれ。
Leave Tobirama to me.
I can't do this without you.
お前なしではやれない。
Help me as the Hokage's right hand...
and as a brother!
火影の右腕として
兄弟として　ともに協力してくれ。
いずれ民もお前のよさに気づく。
その時　二代目として…。
The people will eventually
recognize your merits!
And then,
I'll name you Second Hokage.
After you, I suspect Tobirama
will probably become the Hokage.
お前のあと　おそらくあの
扉間が火影となろう。
そうなれば　うちはは
いずれ消されていく。
When he does, the Uchiha
will be eventually eliminated.
それがわかっていて里を出るよう
うちはの他の者に声をかけたが→
Knowing this,
I've reached out to other Uchiha
about leaving the village.
誰一人
俺についてくる者はいないようだ。
But it seems no one is willing
to follow me.
Madara...
マダラ。
I couldn't protect
my younger brother...
弟も守れなかった。
And it seems I won't be able
to keep the promise I made him...
一族を守ると弟と交わした約束も
守れそうにない。
that I would protect the clan.
守りたい同族からも
信用されていない。
I'm not even trusted
by the clan I want to protect.
That's not true!
そんなことはない。　皆すぐに…。
Everyone is...
Perhaps that time, the ultimatum
I should have given you was
あの時　お前に弟を殺せと
断定するべきだったのかもな。
"to kill your younger brother."
お前は俺を兄弟という。
だが　里のためにどちらを斬れる？
You call me your brother.
But which of us would you kill
for the sake of the village?
I'd like to think that
I know you pretty well.
（マダラ）俺はお前のことを
よくわかっているつもりだ。
I've had enough.
これ以上は　無理だ。
I'm going to leave the village.
俺は里を出て行く。
I've found a different path to take.
俺は別の道を見つけた。
It became clear to me because
we showed each other our guts...
はらわたを見せ合ったからこそ
見えた。
Cooperation is merely
a quiet form of conflict.
協力とはいわば
静かな争いでしかない。
そんなことはない！
俺がそうはさせん！
You're wrong!
I won't let it be like that.
現実をどうとらえるかだ　柱間。
Hashirama, it's what
you make of reality.
ただ　卑屈なのはやめにしよう。
Let's stop being slaves to it.
この世はただの余興と見るほうが
まだ健全だ。
It's healthier to view this world
as merely a sideshow...
俺の話を聞いてるのか　マダラ！
Have you been listening
to me, Madara?!
俺と対等に争えるのは
お前だけだ。
You are the only one
who's an even match for me.
本当の夢の道へ行くまで
お前との戦いを楽しむさ。
I'm looking forward
to the battles we'll fight...
up until the time
I achieve my true dream.
本当の夢って何だ？
What is your true dream?
I thought everything we've aimed for
is here in this village!
俺たちの目指したもんは
この里にあるんだろうが！
お前は見えないのさ。
更にこの先が。
You just can't see it...
What's beyond this...
The dreams of the far future.
先の夢が。
Then tell me about your dreams
of the far future.
だったら　その先の夢ってのを
教えてくれ。
この里の夢とつながるなら
導き役としてお前の力が必要だ。
If it's connected to
this village's dreams,
I need your strength as a leader,
as a senior member.
上役としても。
そして…　友としても。
And...as a friend.
フッ…　つながりなどない。
There is no connection.
そして　お前には決して届かない。
And you'll never reach it.
俺のあとを追いかけても無駄だ。
Chasing after me is useless.
お前なら知ってるだろ。
You, of all people, should know.
No one is capable of
catching me from behind.
(俺の後ろに立てるやつなど
いないと))
＜　そう言って　マダラは里を出た＞
Upon saying those words,
Madara left the village.
＜２人で届いた場所→
We had come this far together.
マダラと俺が望んだ里に
マダラはいなくなった。
And now, Madara was gone from
the village we had created together.
だが世界では
かつての対立したライバル→
But in the world,
everyone respected and copied
our village system of Allied Ninja Clans
うちはと千手が手を組み
作り上げた→
which had been created
忍族連合体である里システムを
皆高く評価し　真似ていった。
by the former warring rivals,
the Uchiha and Senju, joining forces.
Villages like the Village Hidden
in the Leaves
火の国で始まった
木ノ葉隠れの里と→
which began in the Land of Fire,
and its one leader system,
里を治める長というシステムが→
LAND OF FIRE
spread like wildfire across
the Great Nations.
大国に飛び火していったのである。
雷の国には雲隠れの里がおこり
長を雷影と名のり→
In the Land of Lightning,
LAND OF LIGHTNING
Hidden Cloud Village was formed
with its leader named Raikage.
In the Land of Earth,
土の国には岩隠れの里がおこり
長を土影と名のり→
LAND OF EARTH
Hidden Stone Village was formed
with its leader named Tsuchikage.
LAND OF WATER
The Land of Water had the Hidden Mist
with their Mizukage.
水の国には霧隠れの里がおこり
長を水影と名のり→
そして　風の国には→
And in the Land of Wind,
LAND OF WIND
the Hidden Sand was formed and
they named their leader, Kazekage.
砂隠れの里がおこり
長を風影と名のった。
Not only the Great Nations,
大国だけではなく　小国にも
このシステムは受け継がれていった。
but even the smaller nations
adopted this system.
Madara's and my dream had come true.
マダラと俺の夢が叶ったのだ＞
＜忍の子供たちも
戦うことではなく→
Shinobi children learned
and played instead of battling.
学ぶこと　遊ぶことを知り→
酒の味を知るまで
生きていけるようになる＞
And they started living long enough
to even know the taste of alcohol.
But, as if he wanted to destroy
his previous dream...
＜　だが　マダラは
かつての夢を潰すかのごとく→
Madara came back to
attack the Leaf Village.
木ノ葉の里を襲ってきた＞
((柱間：今までのことを
俺たちの努力を→
Will you destroy everything that
we've accomplished until now, Madara?
無駄にするのか　マダラ。
Nothing will come of us
battling each other.
俺とお前が戦ったところで
何も生まれん。
This fight will only...
hurt the village and shinobi!
この戦いは
里と忍を傷つけるだけだ。
It is disrespect toward
our siblings and our comrades!
俺たちの兄弟を　仲間を
侮辱するだけだぞ。
お前に　俺の…。
You know nothing...
俺はお前を殺したくない。
I don't want to kill you!
それは俺を
いつでも殺せるってことか？
Are you implying that
you could kill me at any moment?
No! I'm saying we are friends...
違う。　俺たちは友だと…。
俺はもう　届いたのさ！
I've already...reached it!
しかたない。
Then so be it!
仙法　木遁　真数千手！
Sage Art!
Wood Style...
Shinsu Senju
Veritable 1000-Armed Kan'on!
Here I come, Madara!
いくぞ　マダラ。
来い　柱間！
Come, Hashirama!
（２人）うお～！
頂上化仏！
Chojo Kebutsu!
Artifacts of the Buddha!
スサノオを剥がされたか。　んっ！
He stripped off the Susano'o!
ハァ　ハァ　ハァ…。
いくぞ。
Here I come!
10th Edict on Enlightenment!
廓庵入鄽垂手！
マダラ！
Madara!
Hashirama!
(柱間！))
皆様　お変わりございませんか？
美空ひばりです。
では　最後まで
ごゆっくり　お楽しみください。
（宮本）『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！にっぽんの歌』。
（松丸）夏らしく
ひまわりに囲まれて始まりました。